morning everybody for those of you that
don't know my name is anne-marie super
and I'm the District Attorney of
Sacramento County before I start I'd
like to just do some introductions on
who is here today we have in addition to
myself sheriff Sacramento sheriff Scott
Jones Ventura County District Attorney
Greg Totten Orange County District
Attorney Tony raucous Contra Costa
County District Attorney Dinah Becton
Alameda County District Attorney Nancy
O'Malley Sacramento FBI Special Agent in
Charge Sean Regan United States Attorney
for the Northern District MacGregor
Scott Assemblyman Jim Cooper
Bruce Harrington the brother of Keith
Harrington Irvine Police Department
Chief Mike Hamill and our crime lab
director chip [__]
let me first by saying this the answer
has always been in Sacramento for over
40 years countless victims have waited
for justice over these years hundreds of
individuals have sought justice for
these victims and their families many
have dedicated their virtual entire
professions to seeking this answer for
many of us it was more than a
professional commitment it became
personal for many of us for me here in
Sacramento County in June of 1976 I was
12 I grew up in the East area of
Sacramento near the cluster of where
these crimes began my sisters ranged
from 10 to 16 at the time as I have said
many times over the last 18 years at
least for me for us here in Sacramento
it was a time of innocence in 1976 no
one locked their doors kids rode their
bikes to school parents let their
children play outside the only thing we
were told as a family was he just needed
to be home before dark we did not have
things like cell phones or social media
and then for all of us here in this
community that lived in this community
during this time it all changed
for anyone that lived here in this
community here in Sacramento the
memories are very vivid you can ask
anyone that grew up here everyone has a
story but it must be remembered that it
was not just Sacramento that this deep
this case deeply affected this entire
state and then in June of 2016 at the
40th anniversary for the beginning of
this series the east area rapist a press
conference was held here in Sacramento
hosted by the Sacramento County
Sheriff's Department and the FBI
attended by many agencies across
California that have dedicated their
careers and professions to coming to
some kind of answer the message was
clear
in 2016 the magnitude of this case
demanded that it be solved there were
upwards of 50 rapes 12 murders crimes
that spanned ten years across at least
10 different counties northern Central
and Southern California and it was that
day in June of 2016 that we in Public
Safety reiterated our commitment to the
victims and to justice in this case the
east area rapist the Golden State killer
and it was that day that we embarked
upon what I call our journey for justice
a journey by people across borders
across all professions police officers
FBI agents Crime Lab employees victim
advocates prosecutors community leaders
elected officials all with one mission
to find the answer to give victims a
voice and ultimately to identify this
person and bring him to justice we
brought together we brought teams
together not long after that press
conference we dedicated more resources
more people and we created what I have
called team justice an incredible
collaboration of individuals with one
mission
there are things about that journey and
that commitment that each of us knew the
answer was and always was going to be in
the DNA
we knew we could and should solve it
using the most innovative DNA technology
available at this time we all knew that
it would take passion we all knew that
it would take persistence last Wednesday
at 8:15 in the evening I received an
email from the daughter of sherry
Domingo who was murdered in Southern
California her name is Debbie she was 15
at the time last Wednesday she emailed
in essence and paraphrase hi Ann Marie
I thought the editing for the recent
documentary was brilliant she quoted
from the show quote this case will be
solved because of sheer persistence she
went on to say I have those words posted
in a few places in my home and my
workplace so I can see them at various
times throughout the day thank you for
that persistence I have faith
we all knew as part of this team that we
were looking for a needle in a haystack
but we also all knew that the needle was
there in the last six days and I
emphasize the last six days that passion
that persistence and the knowledge
finally came to an answer in this
building behind us here our crime lab
crime lab employs DNA analysts who work
tirelessly in the last few days to
provide that answer yesterday an arrest
warrant was issued a complaint was filed
charging that individual with two counts
of murder with special circumstances for
the murder of Brian and Katie Maggiore
here in Sacramento in February 1978 it
is fitting that today is national DNA
day we found the needle in the haystack
and it was right here in Sacramento and
with that I would like to introduce our
sheriff Scott Jones
good afternoon before I talk a little
bit about this case I'd like to make
just a couple preliminary comments when
I became sheriff in Sacramento in 2010
there were very few outstanding cases
that drew the passion and the interest
and the dogged determination to solve as
the east area rapist the sheriff that I
took over from Sheriff John McGinnis who
is here with us today told me about the
importance of it and I don't know that I
fully appreciated it at that time but I
can tell you that without exception
weekly and sometimes more I get
telephone calls or emails to this day
from former employees former detectives
community members from all over this
country that believe that they know or
at least have some information on who
the east area rapist was I committed
then to do everything that I could to
solve it and had a lot of conversations
early on with district attorney Schubert
about how we could do it and those
discussions really touched the passion
of both of us to solve this case both of
us committed the best and the brightest
or hand-picked folks to oversee the
resolution of this case and gave
virtually unlimited resources and
freedom to pursue whatever leads and
technology currently existed said I can
tell you that over the last few days as
information started to point towards
this individual we started some
surveillance we were able to get some
discarded DNA and we were able to
confirm what we thought we already knew
that we had our man and yesterday
afternoon in a perfectly executed arrest
my detectives arrested James Joseph
D'Angelo 72 years old living in Citrus
Heights
I can tell you that although it was DNA
ultimately that led us down the right
road there were a lot of places that
road could have led I don't want to
underscore I can't underscore enough the
absolute human factor the dogged
determination of not only the detectives
working on this case but the passion of
the district attorney myself the
community and the victims it's all too
often we forget about talking about the
victims and today we at least brought
the first step towards closure for those
victims of these horrendous crimes so I
want to thank not only the district
attorney in the crime lab and the DNA
that helped us get here but my own
detectives and the detectives from all
of these folks represented by the
leaders standing behind me when we put
together this working group two years
ago and brought in the FBI who was more
than happy to be part of this team and
effort we had no way of knowing that
we'd be standing here talking about the
resolution of all of these crimes so I
have to thank them and again underscore
the importance of the human factor and
the dogged determination and passion of
the individuals and human beings that
led us down the right road to this
individual today I want to now introduce
the District Attorney of Ventura County
Ventura County mr. Greg Totten
good morning I'm very pleased to
announce that this morning in Ventura
County we have filed capital murder
charges against mr. diangelo for the
March 1980 murders of Lyman and Charlene
Smith our complaint alleges two counts
of first degree murder with three
special circumstances namely multiple
murders murder during the commission of
a rape and murder during the commission
of a burglary
now while this filing is just the
beginning of the prosecution of mr.
D'Angelo it is the culmination of a
decades-long unrelenting investigation
that singularly focused on bringing this
rapist and killer to justice the arrest
and charging of D'Angelo frankly would
not have been possible without the
visionary and innovative leadership of
my friend Sacramento District Attorney
and Murray Schubert and I want to thank
her for doing such a wonderful job in
this effort she had the foresight to put
together a statewide task force of as a
sheriff mention some of the best and
brightest law enforcement professionals
in the country I also want to thank
sheriff Scott Jones for the tremendous
resources they devoted to this
investigation and for the brilliantly
executed apprehension of D'Angelo I also
want to thank my own Sheriff's
Department for their great work in the
crime lab and in the investigation as
well as the Ventura police department
which was the original investigation
investigating agency of the Lyman and
Charlene Smith murder this 1980 murderer
has
long been a source of fear and anger in
the neighborhood in which it occurred in
the community and indeed throughout all
of Ventura County this is a case that
much like the rapes that occurred here
in the Sacramento area literally struck
terror in the hearts of Ventura County
residents it also as we know was a
source of great frustration for law
enforcement over a prolonged period
autonomy in fact this murder was among
the first cases I was ever assigned to
work on as a young law clerk in the
District Attorney's Office in 1981 at
that time we had no idea that this
killer was connected to so many other
crimes but thankfully with the advent of
DNA in the late 1980s our understanding
of this case its depth its complexity
its geographic reach and the sheer scope
of violent crimes changed forever
we recognized at that time we were
dealing with a serial killer and at that
time at a time when law enforcement is
unfortunately under so much criticism I
want the public to know that the work on
this case reflects the very best the
very highest standards in the knowable
and dedicated and courageous police
profession the men and women of this
task force did devoted incalculable
hours tens of thousands of hours to this
case throughout that effort they never
gave up they never lost their resolve
they never relented and today's
announcement of charges being filed
against this man this killer this rapist
is the direct result of their effort
and so now a new phase begins
and as we commence the charging and
prosecution of D'Angelo this two will be
a team effort involving many
jurisdictions working collaboratively
and collectively together beyond the
significant court proceedings that lie
ahead and the immense investigation that
is still ongoing ongoing as we speak
we are committed we are determined and
we will God willing hold this man fully
accountable for his crimes thank you and
it's now my pleasure to introduce the
Honorable Tony Rowe caucus District
Attorney of Orange County
Joseph James D'Angelo has been called a
lot of things by law enforcement he's
been called the Eastside rapist he's
been called the buy/sell you ransack er
the original Night Stalker
and the Golden State Killer today it's
our pleasure to call him defendant his
12-year reign of terror lasted from June
from 1974 through May 4th of 1986 he
started with ransacking sexual assaults
rape moved down the state from
Sacramento County and ending in Orange
County from 1980 to 1986 when he was
committing his murders in Orange County
I was a member of the Orange County
District Attorney's Homicide panel and
aware of these unsolved cases and just
hoping and wishing to someday we would
be able to find out who this killer was
the quest to solve this case
was of course very personal to mr. Bruce
Harrington his brother and sister-in-law
were murdered in the most god-awful way
and he worked with the Orange County
District Attorney's Office and other
offices to write and support an
initiative that later became proposition
69 and prop 69 was a proposition that
was turned into law and it was a
proposition that required everybody
arrested for a felony in this state and
some misdemeanors to give a DNA sample
and it very very substantially increased
the DNA database of of California in
Orange County still keeping this case in
mind by the way that case was a strong
incentive to work on developing this
this database the California state
database which now has about 2 million
profiles in the database and in the
meantime the Orange County District
Attorney's Office started our own local
DNA database and we've put about a
hundred and seventy thousand DNA
profiles of individuals who have
committed crime in Orange County in our
database all the time we had this case
in mind
eventually hoping to solve this case so
we've been working vigorously together
with this task force that you've been
hearing about we've been working with
them for since since the original
meeting that district attorney and
Murray Schubert put together here in in
Sacramento and and Annemarie I want to
thank you for doing that that was that
was a it was a great thing to to to
Reese Park this this investigation to
put this task force together it was
something I'm sure all of the different
agencies throughout the county who were
involved had the case in mind always
wanted to solve the case worked on it
you know whenever
they could but with this task force it
was a concerted effort we put resources
on it we put full-time people on it and
I want to thank the people from my
office the people who worked tirelessly
on this case to work to to to attempt to
solve the case and I just think it's
it's wonderful that that it was
eventually solved in in Sacramento and I
want to take the time to a little bit of
time just a moment to recognize that
remember the victims from Orange County
August 19th 1980 the defendant Joseph
D'Angelo is accused of brutally
murdering 24-year old Keith Harrington
and 28 year-old Patrice Harrington in
their Dana Point home he's also accused
of raping and sexually assaulting
Patrice on February 5th 1981 the
defendant is accused of raping sexually
assaulting and murdering 28 year old
Manuela Wickham in Irvine three months
later
years later on May 4th 1986 D'Angelo is
accused of raping sexually assaulting
and murdering 18 year olds Janelle Cruz
in her home we've always believed at
least for many years that this case
would begin and end with DNA this
defendants been able to live free in a
nice suburb in Sacramento our team is
going to work hard to make sure that he
never gets out
we're going to be working together to
make determinations about what the
team's going to be that tries em where
he's gonna be tried and so forth all of
those things who are going to be
answered in in in a short time one other
note in 2016
myself my office worked very hard with
Ventura County District Attorney Greg
Totten and with Sacramento County
District Attorney Anna Marie Schubert to
keep and to reform the death penalty and
that was a successful effort it was a
hard effort but it was a successful
effort so now as we proceed forward with
this case that remains a relevant effort
I just want to say that finally after
all these years the haunting question of
who committed these terrible crimes has
been put to rest
now mr. Bruce Harrington is here and
you've heard his name I want to
introduce you to mr. Bruce Harrington
mr. Harrington if you would step forward
please
fifty-one rapes and twelve murders
today I'd like to speak to the
multi-generation hundreds and hundreds
of multi-generational victims of this
staggering crime spree
it is time for all victims to grieve and
to take measure
one last time
to bring closure to the anguish that
we've all suffered for the last 40
some-odd years it is time for the
victims to begin to heal so long overdue
[Music]
for law enforcement bravo Bravo Bravo
their tenacity their patience their
unrelenting focus a shout-out for Toni
raucous for Steve Cooley for Lisa con
Amory Schubert Jen Scully
Larry Poole the names go on and we've
known many many of them over the years
today is also a reaffirmation of the
power and the Public Safety that's
associated with forensic DNA technology
I began my quest in the mid 90s when DNA
finally came of force into the world of
forensic science my brother and his wife
were killed in 80 so it was 15 years
until we finally heard that there was a
DNA sample taken from our crime scene
and as the years rolled on there were
other DNA samples that became common to
one unknown perpetrator
it's been a struggle to bring DNA in
California to the forefront of that
forensic crime scene investigation tool
surprisingly when I looked at the
situation in the late 90s California was
a laggard Virginia Florida some of the
other more progressive states on the
East Coast were light years a hilla
California I spent time in Sacramento in
the early 2000s appearing before
assembly and Senate Public Safety
committees pleaing that they embrace the
power of DNA and frankly I ran into a
buzz saw of opposition
so in 2003 it became apparent that
nothing was going to happen through
Sacramento senator Burton on the Senate
Public Safety Committee my nemesis I
shamed you then and I shame you now you
were wrong
DNA what it's not all about it's a
three-legged stool the DNA where the
powerful database allows the sample to
be checked to against all cases against
those have been wrongly accused against
those that have been wrongly convicted
and they're sitting in prison over the
years innocence projects have flourished
at law schools in particular using DNA
to try and exonerate those wrongly
committed
I hope these continue there are robust
and active part of the harnessing of DNA
technology DNA also solves current
crimes
this isn't a current crime that's an old
crime but it's finally solved by DNA DNA
also looks out and cuts down on future
crime by using that database to
exonerate those that have been wronged
Isis suspicioned and otherwise allow
current crimes and to be solved
efficiently I end with a plea to the
voters because we are back circulating
another petition this year right now go
out to your Walmart go out your to your
markets and you'll find people gathering
signatures there is a keep California
safe proposition just like there was the
DNA prop 69 position back in 2004 but
here we now now in spring and summer of
18,000 to build up to improve to build
upon and create an even more robust DNA
database in California we need
signatures we need 500,000 signatures by
mid-june it'll be on the November ballot
vote for it and you're going to ask
yourself why is it that we're having to
circulate since its signature petition
again and I would tell you the Burton
Burton accolades that are still
controlling the public safety committees
in the assembly and the Senate again
have disappointed their job and made a
mockery of the name of their committee
the Public Safety Committee
so vote for that proposition and again
to the entire reservoir of victims out
there my sadness is with you for the 51
ladies who were brutally raped in this
crime scene sleep better tonight he
isn't coming through the window he's now
in jail and he's history thank you
[Music]
good afternoon i'm dinah Becton district
attorney for contra costa county for
decades a suspect eluded capture for so
many heartbreaking cases that affected
victims across california these victims
could never truly feel safe even years
after the attacks justice did not come
swiftly as we may have liked or wanted
but now today we will do everything that
we can to bring justice to the victims
that suffered from unspeakable harm from
these horrific crimes the outstanding
work to bring resolution to this case
was in part led by Paul holes who has
investigated this case for over 24 years
Paul recently retired as the chief
forensic services officer for the Contra
Costa County District Attorney's Office
and prior to that he spent 24 years with
the Contra Costa County Sheriff's Crime
Lab Paul spent decades tracking down
leads interviewing victims and
researching new technological advances
while he recently retired from the DA's
office he never gave up on bringing
justice for all of these victims and his
work in using new technologies helped to
solve this case the collaboration
between our office and the various law
enforcement agencies across the state
has now underscored how committed all of
us are to finding a resolution out of a
decade's log of old cold cases and to
bring justice to victims who suffered
both physical and mental pain
their lives were forever changed with
today's welcome news hopefully the
victims can begin to continue on the
long road towards recovery as they
remain resilient in the face of what
happened to them I'd like that like now
to introduce Sean Reagan from the FBI in
Sacramento good afternoon everybody
again I'm Sean Reagan I'm the special
agent in charge of the Sacramento FBI
field office thank you for being here I
would just like to thank all of this
team that's that's behind me and we say
a team truly is a team you can see that
multiple agencies multiple jurisdictions
across the state of California and that
doesn't include all of the leads that
were followed up on in other states and
in in other jurisdictions countless
hours as was mentioned have gone in to
this investigation and this team came
together and and worked consistently to
bring to bring justice in this matter
and to identify a subject responsible
and to solve these heinous crimes and
I'd be remiss when we're talking about a
team if I didn't also include the public
we've reached out to the public
over the years through media and since
2016 we've literally received thousands
of media or of public tips and before
that obviously through the course of the
decades we've received tips from the
public so that's public and the citizens
are part of this team and I'd also like
to thank all of you in the media you
have kept this investigation and these
crimes forefront in people's minds and
forefront in the public so you are part
of the team
and I'd like to step back and recognize
the victims my my partners have done
that we all came together obviously to
bring justice in this case and to solve
the crimes but we came together to bring
solace to the victims and to bring some
resolution and relief and we know that
the pain and anguish has never subsided
through the years and through the
decades but hopefully the significant
action and that we have taken yesterday
and over the last few days will bring
some sense of relief and some sense of
comfort to the many many many victims
and victims families let me also thank
and recognize the line investigators and
the assistant district attorneys that
are working this case across multiple
jurisdictions as far as the FBI is
concerned our Los Angeles field office
our Sacramento field office our
headquarters units Behavioral Analysis
Unit at Quantico have all been involved
in assisting to work this investigation
and the countless hours that went in by
obviously all the agencies recognized
here but the personnel agents
investigators DA's that have have worked
tirelessly and passionately to find
resolution in this case I I thank them
for what they have done to finally bring
closure to this investigation and and I
say that but the investigation continues
and obviously the prosecution will will
just begin and continue so we will
continue we will continue acting as a
team and continue working on this
extremely significant matter and
investigation and prosecution thank you
I'd like to
introduce Nancy O'Malley she is the
district attorney for Alameda County
thank you and good morning or afternoon
thank you for being here it's so
critically important to make sure that
the community knows by our by working
with or through the media about this
incredible outcome of this horrific case
I want to start by adding my thank yous
to the other speakers and particularly
to the leadership of District Attorney
Emory Schubert who did bring us all back
together two years ago all of the
jurisdictions that had a case that we
believed were committed by the same
person not all of the cases had DNA but
many did but all of the cases that we
believe this individual committed are
tied by either his modus operandi or by
DNA and I like all like all of us that
have spoken are so thankful and
appreciative of the work of the teams
and the commitment after so many years
the last few weeks I've been speaking
quite a bit on the issue around testing
sexual assault kits there's a
documentary that has just been released
by produced by Marishka Herrick a from
law and order and that documentary talks
about the significance of not testing
kits and the impact that has on the
victims survivors the impact it has on
society and the impact it has on people
who have been either arrested or wrongly
or wrongly convicted of sexual assault
crimes by using DNA to exonerate part of
what we've been talking about is why
it's so significant for us to get those
kits out of the police evidence lockers
and into crime labs
in 1978 in April a woman and her partner
were asleep they woke up to this
defendant standing over them with a gun
he raped robbed and did follow the same
MO that he had done so many times before
that case occurred in Fremont California
part of Alameda County but that was not
the beginning for me of this individual
this defendant in 1977 when I was in
college I became a volunteer at a rape
crisis center in Contra Costa County and
it was one of the first rape crisis
centers that was created in California
and over the course of this the year in
1977 to 1978 the east area rapist struck
nine times in Contra Costa County and I
was involved as a volunteer advocate
supporting those survivors through the
process at that time one of the things
that led me to become a lawyer was to
change the paradigm of the injustice
that sexual assault and domestic
violence experienced back in those days
we didn't have forensic science like DNA
we didn't have trained forensic of
trained investigators committed
prosecutors when I joined the Alameda
County District Attorney's Office it was
one of my goals to change that paradigm
and I worked tirelessly since that time
through legislation through building
programs and all of the things that we
that we see now so I am particularly
thankful and particularly proud to be
part of this working group to have been
there in the beginning when I've sat
with survivors who had been assaulted by
this guy - now when we can witness him
being held accountable for the crimes
that he committed
there's other legislation we've been
pres passing legislation for some time
around DNA DNA collection testing of
sexual assault kits and in 2015 then
Assemblywoman Nancy Skinner now Senator
Skinner carried legislation that I
sponsored to have those rape kits taken
out of the police evidence room and
brought into a crime lab to be tested
that was followed up by a lot of
advocacy at the national level and so
now there's over 179 million dollars
from the federal government for law
enforcement to be able to have those
kits tested in this case is one example
of so many but a very stark example of
why it's important to have those kits
taken to the crime lab and tested
senator Connie Leiva right now is
carrying a bill that I'm proud to
sponsor that will require those kids to
be taken out of the evidence rooms and
brought into a crime lab what we see is
more than 40% and in some cases higher
than that of a DNA profile that's taken
from us forensic sexual assault kit and
those DNA profiles are being matched
against the database that we just heard
about and those crimes are being solved
not just sexual assault crimes but
murder crimes like this SB 1 449 is on
its way through the legislative process
and we hope and we ask the community to
step up and hear that have their voices
heard that this is critical legislation
to get us to a place where we can brings
justice to those victims that have
suffered this crime in such an in such a
horrific way
we have brought justice to the victims
and to their families in this case
through this arrest and ultimately
through the prosecution justice was
delayed in this case from 1975 to 1986
but we are here now
and the prosecution of this defendant
will occur thank you for being here and
I believe that thank you
hello everyone I'm Sergeant Shawn
Hampton a spokesman for the Sacramento
County Sheriff's Department
right now sheriff Jones and district
attorney and rishu Burt will be
answering questions I understand there's
a lot of questions please be patient
there's no way we will get to them all
but we will do our best
in terms of the type of DNA the only
thing we're prepared to say at this time
is that it was linked through DNA using
current and innovative techniques to do
that as for the other crimes that we
know in California as your list that
you've been handed there's many of them
that match by DNA it is the same DNA as
those that have been charged in the
Ventura case as mr. Totten mentioned but
those that they've just haven't been
charged yet and we're just having gone
at that point this has happened at a
very lightning speed is what I would say
I'm simply gonna say he was identified
through DNA technology
no that's no that's not correct
[Music]
sorry
it was I can tell you and obviously I'm
going to have to be a bit circumspect
because this is still a very active
investigation I mean as we speak there
are warrants being served and interviews
being conducted but what I can tell you
is this has all happened in a very rapid
last few days a very compact period of
time during that time we were able to
surveil him
we got a feel for some of his activities
or lack thereof got kind of some
information regarding his routines we
got some information relative to what he
might do if confronted or apprehended
based on the information we were able to
glean from that surveillance so we
developed a plan to wait for him to come
out of his residence rather than try and
approach him in the residence or when
he's out out and about you know in a
vehicle and so when he came out of his
residence we had a team in place that
was able to take him into custody
he was very surprised by that it looked
as though he might have been searching
his mind to execute a particular plan he
may have had in mind obviously
speculation on my part but he was not
given the opportunity it happened almost
instantaneously and he was taken into
custody without without incident at all
so Joe sorry Joe
well I can't speak to that specifically
but I can say generally you know until
we got a working group together and were
able to associate our you know our he's
East area rapist was someone else's
Golden State killer until we were able
to collaborate and really start looking
at the the MOS the the manner in which
he carried out his crimes and see the
linkages between the crimes and the DNA
that that that tied many of them
together that was a real breaking point
for us and allowed us to not only get
more manpower and more brain power on
this case but allowed us to get more
clues and follow up on more leads in the
back
[Music]
well I can I can confirm that that's the
information we have at the moment now
obviously part of our ongoing
investigation is to kind of work
backwards to try and fill in a lot of
the gaps that we have about his life
from then well actually from before then
to now
we're aware of the same information that
you just described so we're obviously
going to be looking in to see whether
that a hammer or a Darby appellant
played into any of the attacks but it's
again I just just to reiterate it's all
very very Swift and those those details
will be investigated and meted out in
the coming days and weeks
sure I can tell you that he is the next
officer a police officer in two
different agencies one in the Exeter
Police Department which is down in
Visalia from approximately 1973 to 1976
that was roughly during the time as the
Visalia ransac ER cases were occurring I
can then say that he applied for and got
a job with the Auburn Police Department
who was employed there from roughly 1976
to 1979 until he was fired for what you
just heard well very possibly he was
committing the crimes during the time he
was employed as a peace officer and
obviously what we're looking into
whether it was actually on the job or
whether it was you know something that
buy on the job I assume you mean during
the time he was employed do it yeah I
don't know that yet but obviously that's
a question we're gonna want to answer as
well but frontier
I'm glad you asked that question because
that's a question we've gotten from
literally all over the world in the last
24 hours and the answer is no other than
the fact that it like like as was
indicated the media kept this in the
public eye and kept public interest it
kept interest in tips coming in other
than that there was no information
extracted from that book that directly
led to the apprehension he does have a
family I'm not prepared to talk about
what his his family is but he does have
adult children that's really all I'm
prepared to say at the time we don't
with the oil we don't have a full
picture yet we're still filling in that
timeline
[Music]
sure there's um and again I have to be a
bit circumspect here but what I said in
my earlier comments that you know the
DNA actually got us to a road but the
road had many destinations possible
destinations I can first say that even
backing up from the DNA that we would
have never got to a DNA sample or
ability to compare it without the dogged
determination of the detectives on this
case so it's not like it ultimately
would have come to us anyways that's
just simply not the case this was a true
convergence of emerging technology and
dogged determination by detectives so
once we got information that led us to a
general I mean it's almost like the DA
pointed us east so we could exclude
north west and south but we still had to
do a lot of investigative follow-up and
drill down from that direction of east
until we got to this person we did a lot
of exclusions of other folks got this
person that looked like he might be our
guy and then we're able to get at least
an initial discarded DNA sample that
gave us more confidence that this was
our person and we're able to continue
and get a better more workable sample of
DNA I would just say at this point it
was discard a DNA sample
I'm sorry I couldn't hear the question
so I I'm absolutely certain there will
be a trial there remain questions and I
don't want to speak for the prosecution
but obviously there there will have to
be some organization as to who who and
where and and when but I can guarantee
you I mean in this case you know justice
was delayed
it wasn't Swift but I can assure you it
will be sure let me just say something
in terms of the prosecution
there are many jurisdictions involved I
think I mentioned there's ten counties
and so sorry fog so those decisions are
going to be made in the immediate future
this right now as I said before this has
occurred in the last six days and so we
have to take time and do it right and
get together and meet in the best
Methodist district attorney or caucus
said so that will take some time yes sir
[Music]
the answer is No
I think the sheriff mentioned that a
sample was collected from him
abandoned samples so that's what
ultimately changed the tide and I will
say this because everybody's got
questions about the DNA the answer of
your questions is going to come out in a
timely fashion but this case is still
active and so you know as much as you
want to know and I understand it we
can't answer the specifics on the exact
type of technology but that will come
out all right one more question over
here
[Music]
we had I will say we have interviewed
some family members without actually
identifying who they are or what
relationship they are we have
interviewed them and they are as
cooperative and certainly it's quite a
shock to them as you might expect well
we're trying to backtrack that so we're
still working on the the actual timeline
from then to now all right one more
I heard that yesterday but that is not
do you have any information in that
universe or that it's just still in the
open
we have no information the persons link
you to Australia so I think this just
about wraps it up for us today I
understand I understand
listen I understand there's a lot of
questions we have a lot of work to do on
the back end there's a lot of folks
behind me to have to get back to work so
I appreciate your time I appreciate your
patience we will try to field interviews
as information comes available and I
thank you again for coming today